Charles M. Kurtz
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Charles M. Kurtz papers
1843-1990, bulk 1884-1909
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Kurtz, Charles M.
27.6 linear feet
The papers of arts administrator, museum director, collector, dealer, and editor Charles M. Kurtz (1855-1909), measure 28 linear feet and date from 1843-1990 (bulk dates 1884-1909). The bulk of the collection consists of detailed chronological correspondence between Kurtz and his wife and family, friends, colleagues, and business associates that documents many notable exhibitions, galleries, museums, private collections, as well as cities, people, and events of the period. Also found in the collection are Kurtz's diaries, scrapbooks, printed materials, and photographs.
Biographical Note
Charles M. Kurtz's name is known to many scholars and students of American art history. To some he is important for his critical writings, others are interested in his management of exhibitions for the Art Union and the American Art Association. Many are aware of him because of his publication of National Academy Notes, which continued for nine years. Still others are familiar with Kurtz in his role as an art administrator for late 19th century art exhibitions like those at the 1893 Columbian Exposition in Chicago and the St. Louis Fair, or for his accomplishments as the first director of the Albright Gallery in Buffalo, New York. Sometimes researchers have become familiar with his name through the sale catalogue for his considerable collection, which was sold at auction after his death in 1909. His career, which encompassed the last quarter of the nineteenth century and the first decade of the twentieth century, touched on virtually every aspect of art in America during that period.
Born in 1853 to Davis Brook Kurtz (1826-1906), an attorney, and Julia Wilder, Charles Kurtz enjoyed a genteel upbringing. The Kurtz family originated in Darmstadt, Germany, and migrated to America in the eighteenth century. D.B. Kurtz, a leading member of the Lawrence County bar, was also a vice-president of the National Bank of Lawrence County, Pennsylvania. As a local representative of many important railroad and business interests, he accumulated assets estimated at one million dollars by the time of his death, just three years before that of his son, Charles, the eldest of his five children. Unlike his brothers Louis, who also became an attorney, and Edward, a professor at Columbia University, Charles eschewed a professional career to enter the art world, as did his sisters Emily, an artist, and Catherine, a musician.
After his graduation from Washington and Jefferson College in Washington, Pennsylvania, Kurtz visited the Centennial Exposition, held in 1876 in Philadelphia, before coming to New York to study art at the National Academy of Design. These two activities foreshadowed the direction that his career would eventually take. As the chronology indicates, his early efforts revolve around writing for a variety of publications, most notably, his own National Academy Notes. In 1881 he took what was to be the first of many trips abroad to survey the art scene in Europe. Later in his career, his fascination with foreign art and his own entrepeneurial interests led him to become an outspoken opponent of tariffs on imported art.
Kurtz's personal life changed significantly in 1884 when he met Julia Stephenson, a physician's daughter and fledging art student from Harrodsburg, Kentucky. Throughout their courtship and after their marriage the couple was frequently separated. Consequently, they wrote lengthy letters which document not only their personal relationship but also Kurtz's aspirations and activities in the art world.
With his appointment as one of Halsey C. Ives's (1847-1911) chief assistants of the Fine Arts Department of the World's Columbian Exposition in 1891, Charles Kurtz's career achieved international stature. Among the most notable European artists he introduced into this country through circulating exhibitions were the Glasgow School, the Danish School, the Hungarian artist, Mihaly Munkacsy, and the subject of his final exhibition, the Spanish artist, Sorolla.
Throughout his life, Kurtz was plagued by health problems and, in 1899, illness forced him to resign as Assistant Director of Fine Arts for the United States for the Paris Exposition of 1900. Throughout the following decade, his work was increasingly interrupted by ill health. His death in 1909 at the age of 54, while sudden, was not entirely unexpected. However it most certainly cut short a cosmopolitan career that encompassed virtually every aspect of the art world and the pertinent issues of the day.
Kurtz is remembered for his editorial work with the National Academy of Design; as Art Director for the Southern Exposition, 1883-1886, and the St. Louis Exposition, 1894-1899 (where he introduced the Glasgow School of Painting); and as Assistant Chief/Director for the World's Columbian Exposition, the 1900 Paris Exposition, and the 1904 Louisiana Purchase Exposition. He was also director of the Buffalo Fine Arts Academy.
Date Event
1855 Charles McMeen Kurtz born
1876 receives B.S. degree from Washington and Jefferson College, Washington, Pennsylvania
1876-78 studies at the National Academy of Design, N.Y. with Lemuel Wilmarth and William Morgan; writes a column, "New York Letters," for The Courant published in New Castle, Pennsylvania
1878 edits a small daily paper published during a "National Camp Meeting for the promotion of Holiness" held that summer in New Castle, Pa.; its critical stance resulted in his public denouncement and earned him a reputation as a journalist in western Pennsylvania; receives M.A. from Washington and Jefferson College
1878-79 becomes the local editor of The Guardian of New Castle
1879 publishes The Daily Reporter, a financial success
1881 publishes the first issue of National Academy Notes; travels in Europe, spending time in England, Holland, Belgium, Germany, Switzerland, Italy and France (Paris)
1881-82 prepares Illustrated Notes for Metropolitan Museum of Art exhibition
1882 writes "Art Notes" in The New York Tribune and resigns Dec. 23rd
1882-83 accepts position to write for Music and Drama, a new daily paper
1883 becomes the general manager of the American Art Union; exhibits a large collection of Art Union paintings in Buffalo, N.Y. and Louisville, Ky., where they became part of the Southern Exposition's first great art display
1883-86 accepts offer to become Director of the Art Department, Southern Exposition, Louisville, Kentucky
1884 edits Art Union magazine until December; applies for position to head the Art Department of the New Orleans World's Fair in September
1884-86 accepts a position offered by the American Art Association; terminates uncongenial relationship in March, 1886
1885 writes catalogues for the sale of the George Seney Collection and for the Watts exhibition at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York; October 1, marries Julia Stephenson (1861-1931), daughter of Dr. A. T. Stephenson of Harrodsburg, Kentucky; they had two daughters who survived them: Julia Wilder Kurtz (1889-1977), and Isabella Starkweather Kurtz (1901-1991); another daughter, Elizabeth Stephenson Kurtz (1886-1897), predeceased them
1886 terminates employment with the Art Association; daughter, Elizabeth Stephenson Kurtz, born
1886-87 manages the circulation of Mihaly Munkacsy's Christ Before Pilot for Charles Sedelmeyer to American venues: New York, Boston, St. Louis, Cincinnati, Kansas City, Minneapolis, Saint Paul, Nashville, Phildelphia, Indianapolis; tour generates $90,000 in ticket receipts
1889-91 February 24, appointed art critic ("Art Notes") and book reviewer for New York Daily Star; later literary and art editor of the Sunday Star
1890 writes for the Sunday edition The Press, a New York paper
1891 writes for The World; art editor for The New York Recorder; contributes to the New York Truth
1891-93 contributes to Chicago Evening Post; writes artist biographies for The Chicago Graphic, a regional magazine; appointed Assistant Chief of the Department of Fine Arts of the World's Columbian Exposition
1894 contributes column, "Art at the Exposition" to St. Louis Life
1895 tours Denmark, Scotland, and France during the summer on behalf of the St. Louis Exposition
1894-99 appointed Director of the Art Department of the St. Louis Annual Exposition
1896 elected member of The Japan Society, London
1897 daughter, Elizabeth (Daisy), dies
1898 receives a diploma and medal "in recognition of valuable services in connection with the Fine Arts Exhibit" from the directors of the Trans-Mississippi International Exposition, Omaha
1899 appointed Assistant Director of Fine Arts for the United States Commission to the Paris Exposition of 1900; resigned in July due to ill health
1901-04 appointed Assistant Chief of the Department of Art of the Louisiana Purchase Exposition, August
1901 daughter, Isabella Starkweather Kurtz, born
1902 receives honorary Ph.D from Washington and Jefferson College "in recognition of distinguished ability and services as an art critic and writer"
1905 receives the cross of the Order of Merit from Prince Ferdinand of Bulgaria; appointed Director, Buffalo Fine Arts Academy and Albright Art Gallery, Buffalo, New York, in January; exhibits Glasgow paintings at Albright Art Gallery from November until the following April
1906 writes Academy Notes, a bulletin pubished by the Buffalo Fine Arts Academy and the Albright Art Gallery; father, D.B. Kurtz, dies in Newcastle, Pennsylvania
1907 accused of importing German pictures free of duty for exhibition purposes and then selling some for profit
1908 Honorary Doctor of Philosophy degree conferred by Washington and Jefferson College
1909 Charles M. Kurtz dies in Buffalo, New York on March 21
1910 Sale of the private collection of Charles M. Kurtz at auction, Fifth Avenue Art Galleries, February 24-25
1931 Widow, Julia Stephenson Kurtz dies October 30
1977 Daughter, Julia Wilder Kurtz, dies
1991 Daughter, Isabel Starkweather Kurtz, dies in Buffalo, N.Y.; remaining Charles M. Kurtz Papers bequeathed to the Archives of American Art and the National Academy of Design, New York
Scope and Content Note
The Charles M. Kurtz papers measure 27 linear feet and date from 1843 to 1990 with the bulk of the material dating from 1884 to 1909. The bulk of the collection consists of chronological correspondence between Kurtz and his family, most notably his wife, friends, colleagues, and business associates. Kurtz's letters are amazingly detailed and document many notable exhibitions, galleries, museums, private collections, as well as cities, people, and events of the period. The letters between Kurtz and his wife are most interesting for their descriptive commentary on late 19th century life and offer a complete picture of Kurtz's activities. Many of Kurtz's letters to Halsey C. Ives can be found in the Halsey C. Ives Papers. Some of the letters in the collection are illustrated. Also found in the collection are Kurtz's diaries, scrapbooks, printed materials, and photographs.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into twelve series.
Series 1: Biographical Information, 1885-1931, undated
Series 2: Correspondence, 1843-1940, undated
Series 3: Circulars/Requests for Submissions of Works of Art, 1886-1905
Series 4: Legal Records, 1881-1928
Series 5: Financial Records, 1870-1989, undated
Series 6: Diaries, 1894-1901
Series 7: Notes and Writings, 1872-1980, undated
Series 8: Scrapbooks, 1878-1909
Series 9: Printed Material, 1873-1990, undated
Series 10: Photographs, 1898-1990
Series 11: Photographs of Works of Art, undated
Series 12: Miscellany, undated
Related Material
The St. Louis Exposition/Halsey C. Ives papers in the Archives of American Art contain material relating to Charles M. Kurtz.
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
National Academy of Design (U.S.); Albright Art Gallery (Buffalo, N.Y.); Buffalo Fine Arts Academy; World's Columbian Exposition (1893: Chicago, Ill.); Southern Exposition (1885: Louisville, Ky.); Saint Louis Exposition and Music Hall Association (1883-1902: Saint Louis, Mo.); Exposition universelle internationale de 1900 (Paris, France); Louisiana Purchase Exposition (1904: Saint Louis, Mo.)
Subjects-Topical:
Arts administrators -- United States; Museum directors -- New York (State) -- Buffalo; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Art critics -- United States; Art museums -- Buffalo (N.Y.); Art criticism; Art -- Private collections; Art, Scottish; Exhibitions -- United States; Glasgow school of painting; Editors -- United States
Types of Materials:
Address books; Works of art; Diaries; Menus; Photographs; Photogravures; Sketches; Visiting cards; Engravings; Etchings; Lithographs; Oil paintings; Tempera paintings
Names:
Avery, Samuel Putnam, 1822-1904; Abbey, Edwin Austin, 1852-1911; Irwin, Benoni, 1840-1896; Clarke, Thomas B. (Thomas Benedict), 1848-1931; Cesnola, Luigi Palma di, 1832-1904; Hallowell, Sara; Hambidge, Jay, 1867-1924; Hasbrouck, Du Bois Fenelon, b.1860; Ives, Halsey Cooley, 1847-1911; Kurtz, Davis Brook Kurtz, 1826-1906; Kurtz, Julia Stephenson; Pluschow, Guglielmo photographer; Reid, Alexander; Rhodes, Charles Ward, d. 1905; Richardson, Mary Curtis, 1848-1931; Sedelmeyer, Charles; Starkweather family; Thum, Patty P., 1853-1926; Wanamaker, John, 1838-1922; Wickenden, Robert J.; American Art Association; Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts
Provenance
For many years, the Kurtz Papers were thought to have been destroyed in a fire. Isabel Kurtz, a school teacher who lived with her older sister in Buffalo, New York, was vague when initially approached about her father's papers by Archives Regional Director, Robert Brown in the mid-1980s. However upon her death in 1991, her will revealed that the papers were indeed in her house in Buffalo and the bulk of them were bequeathed to the Archives of American Art. Paintings and a diary relating to the Glasgow School were given to the Yale Center for British Art. That diary has subsequently been duplicated on microfilm and is now also available in the Archives. Scorch marks on some of the papers and also on the paintings given to Yale suggest that there was indeed a fire. The material that was not bequeathed to the Archives included duplicates of printed documents along with books from the Kurtz library and a coin collection, all of which were dispersed in an estate auction that was held in Buffalo in 1991.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Patrons must use microfilm copy.
Alternative Forms Available
Most of the collection has been filmed on microfilm reels 4804-4826. The remaining documents were not filmed as they were represented elsewhere in the collection of the Archives of American Art. The microfilm is also available for interlibrary loan.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Information, 1885-1931, undated, Series 1:
  This series includes résumés and reminiscences by and about Kurtz, obituaries of Kurtz and other family members, and miscellaneous biographical information. The types of material included are newspaper clippings, handwritten and typed manuscripts, drafts and printed matter.
  Résumés and reminiscences consist of a press release/résumé by Charles M. Kurtz, "A New Appointment," on his appointment as Assistant Director of the U. S. Exposition, 1900 Paris World's Fair; a biography of Kurtz; and a reminiscence by Kurtz's daughter, Isabella Starkweather Kurtz.
  - Résumés and Reminiscences, undated (Reel 4804, Frame 3-13)
  - Obituaries of Charles M. Kurtz, 1909 (Reel 4804, Frame 19-42)
  - Obituaries of Kurtz's father, D. B. Kurtz, 1906 (Reel 4804, Frame 44-52)
  - Obituaries of Kurtz's mother-in-law, Elizabeth A. Stephenson and wife, Julia Stephenson Kurtz. 1906, 1931 (Reel 4804, Frame 65-69)
  - Miscellaneous biographical information, wedding invitation, 1885 (Reel 4804, Frame 2)
  - Miscellaneous biographical information, certificates of commendation, awards, undated (Reel 4804, Frame 53-63)
  - Miscellaneous biographical information, passport, 1906 (Reel 4804, Frame 64)
  - Miscellaneous biographical information, letter from Mary T. Martin (relative) detailing Kurtz genealogy, undated (Reel 4818, Frame 1236-1239)
- Correspondence, 1843-1940, undated, Series 2:
  Charles M. Kurtz had a wide circle of friends and acquaintances that often overlapped his personal friends and professional colleagues with his career activities. Certain individuals whose names may not be particularly well known, such as the artists, D.F. Hasbrouck, William Morgan and Patty Thum, for example, were both personal and professional friends. Their letters, often seeking Kurtz's help, are informative about their own and Kurtz's careers. Kurtz's close friends, the Starkweathers, his own relatives, and his wife's family, the Stephensons, were particularly interested in Kurtz's professional activities and also kept him informed. His sister, Emily "Clootie" Kurtz, for example, also studied art in New York under H. Siddons Mowbray and her letters, especially those written while she was in Europe in 1891, occasionally commented on the art world of the day. His father, D.B. Kurtz, an important attorney for railroad and banking concerns in western Pennsylvania, details many of his legal activities in his letters to his son. His letters have been highlighted because of his own prominence and their references to his son's collecting activities, for which he often advanced funds. There is also the occasional letter from the distinguished New York photographer, William Kurtz, who was not related to Charles M. Kurtz. His letters have been indicated by the inclusion of his first name so as to distinguish him from the Kurtz family.
  Many of the names noted in the description of Kurtz's personal and professional correspondence represent individuals of interest to art historians and those studying American social history. Although some merely record a brief professional contact with Kurtz (e.g. Stanford White sending regrets), they do place the individual at a certain place in time. Several correspondents who contacted Kurtz throughout his career solely on behalf of personal concerns (e.g. his college fraternity) have not been noted. In the case of a letter written on behalf of a well known individual or organization by someone whose name may not be immediately recognizable, the appropriate identification has been indicated in brackets the first time it appears, e.g. James Grant [for John Wanamaker].
  The correspondence between Kurtz and his wife is among the richest in the collection and most interesting for its descriptive commentaries on late 19th century life. Consequently the most successful method of using the Kurtz papers is for the researcher to identify a date and/or event for which information is needed (e.g. the blizzard of 1888) and then read their correspondence for that period. Another approach for arriving at useful information (e.g. a description of the Baltimore collector, Benjamin Walters' house) is to consult the chronology and ascertain Kurtz's itinerary during a given period. He invariablycomments on notable people, places and the ambiance in the cities that he visited while managing various expositions and exhibitions. Gaps in the correspondence between husband and wife usually correspond to periods when they were living or travelling together.
  Many letters are illustrated (see Index), usually by Kurtz himself. The majority of these are to his wife. Some may be difficult to decipher because a fire scorched some of the letters while they were in the possession of the Kurtz family.
  Reel 4805 contains letters, primarily from artists and art committee members; concerning loans for the Southern Exposition, Louisville, Kentucky (Aug.16-Oct.25, 1884) and related details. Frequent correspondence to and from Charles Kurtz to his fiancée Julia Stephenson is regularly interspersed beginning in September, 1884. Many of the letters from E. Wood Perry refer to the Art Union; others from Kurtz refer to the Art Association.
  See Index for List of Illustrated Letters
  Index: List of Illustrated Letters
  American Art Association galleries with Dutch fireplace: AAA 4805 (1345) letter from CMK to Julia Stephenson, Dec. 17, 1884 by CMK, with extensive description of galleries at Six East Twenty-third Street (Madison Square South, entrance on B'way).
  Portrait of Charles M. Kurtz, 1884 by Julia Stephenson: AAA 4805 (1409) end of year note with illustration
  Self-Portrait (caricature) of Charles M. Kurtz, undated, as signature on brief letter to Julia W. Kurtz: AAA 4804 (394)
  Holiday banner of cherubs on 1884 letter by Julia S. to CMK: AAA 4805 (1414)
  Anonymous portrait, pencil sketch, circa 1877: AAA 4804 (753)
  Pencil drawing of train "The Next Station is New Castle:" AAA 4804 (783)
  Floor plan of Detroit house of Col. Crowell: AAA 4804 (1152) (Col Crowell was brother-in-law of a Mr. Elwood of the Wayne Co. National Bank. Kurtz says he "lives in probably the finest house in Detroit. I never saw more elegant or more beautiful furnishing. It is really finer than that in the Power's establishment in Rochester! 3 page description follows of the furnishings: carved woodwork, stained glass etc. also mentions he went to see "an artist named Melchers with Bacher")
  Pencil sketch by Julia Stephenson of herself "pulling" CMK's wiskers: AAA 4804 (1235), November 23, 1883 letter, page 9
  Post card sketch "The Boy That Did As He Pleased," Dec. 1883 by CMK to Julia Stephenson, sketch of cow & boy in meadow: AAA 4804 (1238)
  Caricature of CMK by himself as signature on letter to Julia Stephenson, Dec. 2, 1883 letter: AAA 4804 (1253)
  Double Self Portrait of Julia Stephenson as a "coquette," Dec. 9, 1883 letter to CMK: AAA 4804 (1254)
  Upraised hand of truth from CMK to Julia Stephenson, Dec. 1883: AAA 4804 (1264)
  Logo designs on back of envelope, with upraised hand, & "North Gallery" with palettee, 1885: AAA 4806 (81)st
  Pencil sketch (finished drawing) of child sitting under tree with calligraphic date "June second, 1885" [a copy of Mrs. Loop's picture in my "81 book" of Mrs. Loop's daughter] see letter, June 14, 1885 AAA 4806 (634): AAA 4806 (623)
  Monogram designed for pin given as gift for bridesmaids at wedding of CMK & Julia Stephenson: AAA 4806 (1039)
  Sketch of a painting by unidentified artist acquired by CMK in letter to JSK, June 11, 1886: AAA 4807 (401)
  Sketch of Victorian era townhouse: AAA 4822 628
  Street in Bologna, Italy: AAA 4822 (1083)
  Poem circa March, 1897 with self-portrait caricature: AAA 4823 (240)
  Maps: Massachusetts, Boston, & handwritten, of Mt. Vernon St. in letter from CMK to JSK, July 8, 1887: AAA 4808 (480)
  Floor plan of Kurtz's room at 123 E. 23rd: AAA 4808 (1211)
  Self-portrait for his daughter, July 26, 1888: AAA 4809 (279)
  Self-portrait sketch "For Daisy," Oct. 20, 1888: AAA 4809 568
  Street map of section of New Orleans, Jan. 1889: AAA 4809 (986)
  Floor plan, Washington Artillery bldg., New Orleans (Muncky. exh), Jan. 26, 1889: AAA 4809 1014)
  Marine sketch by J. C. Nicoll, March 28, 1889: AAA 4809 (1250)
  Sketch of building and floor plan of St. Louis Museum by Halsey C. Ives, June 7, 1889: AAA 4809 (1484)
  Sketch by Charles M. Kurtz of curtain valence, June 12, 1889: AAA 4809 (1505)
  Sketch by Charles M. Kurtz of General di Cesnola's [director, Metropolitan Museum of Art] country house in Mt. Kisco, N.Y., August 5, 1889: AAA 4810 (195)
  Small, self-portrait sketch by Charles M. Kurtz at end of letter to his daughter, Nov. 17, 1891: AAA 4811 (238)
  Small, self-portrait sketch by Charles M. Kurtz at end of letter to his daughter, Nov. 27, 1891: AAA 4811 (308)